Guide to the Tamiment Playhouse Alumni Oral History Collection OH.031
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Tamiment Playhouse Alumni Oral History Collection
1955-1988
OH.031
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
3.92 linear feet in 1 record carton, 1 manuscript box, and five card catalog drawers.
The Tamiment Playhouse, located at the Socialist Party's retreat, Camp Tamiment, in Pennsylvania's Pocono mountains, became an important workshop and a major creative outlet for theater, dance, film, and television in the mid-twentieth century. Actors such as Danny Kaye, Bea Arthur, Imogene Coca, and Carol Burnett; directors Max Liebman, Herb Ross, and Joe Layton; choreographer Jerome Robbins; and writers Woody Allen and Neil Simon are a small sampling of the major entertainment figures nurtured at Camp Tamiment. Much of the original material performed at Tamiment found its way to the professional stage, Broadway, and television. All interviewees were involved in the Tamiment Playhouse, mainly in the 1950s. Most of the interviews consist of recollections of the Tamiment summer theater, as well as discussions about the importance of the Playhouse for Broadway. Interviews were conducted between 1980 and 1988 by Andrew Horn of the Tamiment Playhouse Archives and by NYU Performance Studies graduate student Martha S. LoMonaco for her dissertation and subsequent book on the Tamiment Playhouse, entitled Every Week a Broadway Revue. The collection also contains live recordings of shows at the Tamiment Playhouse, dating from 1955-1960.
Horn, Andrew
LoMonaco, Martha Schmoyer
Historical/Biographical Note
The Tamiment Playhouse was located at Camp Tamiment in Pennsylvania's Pocono Moutains. The camp was a summer resort opened in 1921 by the People's Educational Camp Society and affiliated with the Socialist Party's Rand School of Social Science. Started as a means to entertain campers, the playhouse became an important workshop and a major creative outlet for theater, dance, film, and television in the mid-twentieth century. Actors such as Danny Kaye, Bea Arthur, Imogene Coca, and Carol Burnett; directors Max Liebman, Herb Ross, and Joe Layton; choreographer Jerome Robbins; and writers Woody Allen and Neil Simon are a small sampling of the major entertainment figures nurtured at Camp Tamiment. Much of the original material performed at Tamiment found its way to the professional stage and finally Broadway.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Due to the fragile nature of the original media, recordings without access CDs listed in the findings aid must have digital surrogates made before they can be listened to by researchers. To request digitization of materials, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu.
Scope and Content Note
The Oral Histories series is comprised of sixty-three interviews that were conducted between 1980 and 1988 by Andrew Horn of the Tamiment Playhouse Archives and by NYU Performance Studies graduate student Martha S. LoMonaco for her dissertation and subsequent book on the Tamiment Playhouse, Every Week a Broadway Revue. Most of the interviews consist of recollections of the Tamiment summer theater, as well as discussions about the importance of the Playhouse for Broadway. Of note in the collection are interviews with Woody Allen, Carol Burnett, Imogene Coca, and Neil Simon. Materials in the Shows series were recorded live on reel to reel audiotape at the Tamiment Playhouse from 1955-1960.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in two series. The first series, Oral Histories, is comprised of LoMonaco's interviews taken in the course of researching for Every Week a Broadway Revue. The second series, Shows, are live recordings of performances at the Tamiment Playhouse from 1955-1960.
Related Archival Materials
Tamiment Library holds several additional collections related to Tamiment Playhouse, Camp Tamiment, and their parent organizations. These include: Tamiment Playhouse Records (TAM.107), Tamiment Playhouse Photographs (PHOTOS.041), Alexander Cohen Tamiment Playhouse Photographs (PHOTOS.080), People's Educational Camp Society and Camp Tamiment Records (TAM.007.003), and Rand School of Social Science Records (Tam.007).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Oral history interviews were donated by Martha S. LoMonaco in 1992.
Tamiment Playhouse.; Camps |z Pennsylvania.; Jewish entertainers |z United States.; Socialism |z United States.; Summer theater |z Pennsylvania |z Pocono Mountains |x History.; Theater |x Political aspects.
- Oral Histories, Bulk, 1980-1988; 1952-1988
  Arrangement
  Series is arranged alphabetically by interviewee surname.
  - Allen, Woody, Dec 09, 1986 (Drawer A, Cassette 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barer, Marshall, Mar 21, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2, Drawer A, Cassette 2 A-D)
  - Berkowitz, Sol, Mar 04, 1986 (Drawer A, Cassette 3 A-B, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bird, Dorothy, Jan 16, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4, Drawer A, Cassette 4 A-B, Box Access Audio 1, Cd 4 Bird 1-2)
  - Blaker, Ben, Sep 27, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5, Drawer A, Cassette 5 A-B)
  - Blaker, Martha & Alex, Oct 21, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6, Drawer A, Cassette 6 A-B)
  - Bock, Jerry, May 13, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7, Drawer A, Cassette 7)
  - Bozeman, Beverly, Oct 27, 1981 (Drawer A, Cassette 8, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brenner, Yvonne, Dec 11, 1981 (Drawer A, Cassette 9, Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bruskine, Perry, Jun 18, 1986
  - Burnett, Carol, Mar 22, 1982 (Drawer A, Cassette 10, Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Carroll, Pat, Jun 09, 1986 (Drawer A, Cassette 11 A-B, Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Coca, Imogene, Mar 11, 1986 (Drawer A, Cassette 12 A-B, Box 1, Folder 12, Box Access Audio 1, Cd Coca 1-2)
  - Connell, Gordon, undated (Drawer A, Cassette 13)
  - Cook, Barbara, Mar 16, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13, Drawer B, Cassette 14)
  - Corey, Irwin, Feb 11, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14, Drawer B, Cassette 15 A-B)
  - Daniels, Danny, Mar 12, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15, Drawer B, Cassette 16)
  - Deems, Mickey, Jan 15, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16, Drawer B, Cassette 17 A-B)
  - Dooley, Paul, Aug 17, 1986 (Drawer B, Cassette 18)
  - Ellstein, Sylvia Regan, Feb 13, 1987 (Drawer B, Cassette 19 A-B, Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Felder, Blanche (Ganz), Apr 29, 1987 (Drawer B, Cassette 20, Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Frankel, Beulah, Apr 03, 1982 (Drawer B, Cassette 21, Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Garrett, Betty, undated (Drawer B, Cassette 22, Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gildermeister, Rick, Oct 28, 1987 (Drawer B, Cassette 23)
  - Gladstone, Saul, Apr 12, 1987 (Drawer B, Cassette 24 A-C, Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Goldfarb, Philip, Feb 09, 1987 (Drawer B, Cassette 25, Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Goren, Lewis, Aug 26, 1985 (Drawer B, Cassette 26 A-B, Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Greene, Milton, Dec 12, 1986 (Drawer B, Cassette 27, Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hack, Moe & Hack Cohen, Paula, Sep 09, 1985 (Drawer C, Cassette 28 A-D, Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hack, Moe & Thomas, Bill, undated (Drawer C, Cassette 29 A-B)
  - Hack, Paula Cohen, Dec 14, 1981 (Drawer C, Cassette 30)
  - Halliday, Buzz, Sep 26, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 27, Drawer C, Cassette 31 A-B)
  - Hayes, Dorsha, Jul 02, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 28, Drawer C, Cassette 32)
  - Hollister, David, Jan 30, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 29, Drawer C, Cassette 33)
  - Holt, Calvin, Jul 07, 1986 (Drawer C, Cassette 34 A-B, Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Josephson, Ben, Oct 30, 1986 (Drawer C, Cassette 35 A-B, Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Kallen, Lucille, Apr 27, 1982 (Box Access Audio 1, Cd Kallen 1, Box 1, Folder 32, Drawer C, Cassette 36 A)
  - Kallen, Lucille, Mar 06, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 32, Drawer C, Cassette 36 B, Box Access Audio 1, Cd Kallen 2)
  - Kemp, Pearl, Nov 21, 1986 (Drawer C, Cassette 37, Box 1, Folder 33, Box Access Audio 1, Cd Kemp 1)
  - Kert, Larry, Dec 05, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 34, Drawer C, Cassette 38)
  - Lawson, Sid, Oct 06, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35, Drawer C, Cassette 39)
  - Levitas, Michael, Apr 21, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 36, Drawer C, Cassette 40)
  - Levitas, Willard, Jun 11, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 37, Drawer C, Cassette 41)
  - Lichtenberg, Daniel, Apr 09, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 38, Drawer D, Cassette 42 A-B)
  - Liff, Biff (Samuel), Jun 07, 1986 (Drawer D, Cassette 43 A-B, Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Meyer, John, Feb 02, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Nye, Anita & Tolken, Mel, undated (Drawer D, Cassette 45)
  - Pockriss, Lee, Mar 13, 1986 (Drawer D, Cassette 46, Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Remo, Ken, Dec 20, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 42, Drawer D, Cassette 47 A-B)
  - Rodgers, Mary (Goettel), Sep 23, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 43, Drawer D, Cassette 48)
  - Rosales, Sylvia Marks, Apr 16, 1982 (Drawer D, Cassette 49 A-B, Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Ross, Mark, Apr 18, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Sandyville Group, Aug 27, 1985 (Drawer D, Cassette 50 A-B, Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Scheiner, Harry, Jun 02, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 47, Drawer D, Cassette 51)
  - Seltzer, Ellen, Jan 01, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 48, Drawer D, Cassette 52)
  - Simon, Danny, Dec 05, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 49, Drawer D, Cassette 53 A-B)
  - Simon, Neil, Jan 20, 1988 (Drawer D, Cassette 54, Box 1, Folder 50, Box Access Audio 1, Cd N. Simon 1)
  - Simone, Arlene, Feb 23, 1987 (Drawer D, Cassette 55)
  - Starbuck, James, Dec 12, 1985 (Drawer D, Cassette 56 A-B, Box 1, Folder 51, Box Access Audio 1, Cd Starbuck 1-2)
  - Stich, Faye Stern, Jul 24, 1985 (Drawer D, Cassette 57)
  - Tamiment Playhouse Performance, 1952 (Drawer E, Cassette 58 A-C)
  - Theodore, Lee, Nov 10, 1981 (Drawer E, Cassette 59, Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Tolken, Mel, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Wagner, Charles, Jul 09, 1986 (Cassette 60, Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Wagner, Frank, Dec 30, 1981 (Drawer E, Cassette 61, Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Weiner, John, Jun 03, 1986 (Drawer E, Cassette 62 A-B, Box 1, Folder 56)
- Shows, 1955-1960
  Series is arranged chronologically.
  - Ninth show, Do it yourself, probably Aug 27, 1955 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Tenth show, People will talk at 3.75, Sep 03, 1955 (Box 1, Reel 2)
  - Twelfth show, 1955 (Box 1, Reel 3)
  - Third show, Perchance, Jul 15, 1956 (Box 1, Reel 4)
  - Second show, Spic n Span, Jul 07, 1956 (Box 1, Reel 5)
  - Ninth show, Time was, Aug 25, 1956 (Box 1, Reel 6)
  - Tenth show, We promise the moon, Sep 01, 1956 (Box 1, Reel 7)
  - Twelfth show, first act, 1956 (Box 1, Reel 8)
  - Twelfth show, second act, 1956 (Box 1, Reel 9)
  - First show, Do it yourself, Jun 29, 1957 (Box 1, Reel 10)
  - Fourth show, Do it yourself, Jul 20, 1957 (Box 1, Reel 11)
  - Twelfth show, Do it yourself, Sep 07, 1957 (Box 1, Reel 12)
  - Third show, High hopes, Jul 18, 1959 (Box 1, Reel 13)
  - Fourth show, Red hot, Jul 25, 1959 (Box 1, Reel 14)
  - Fifth show, Isn't America fun, Aug 01, 1959 (Box 1, Reel 14)
  - Fifth show, Isn't America fun, Aug 01, 1959 (Box 1, Reel 15)
  - Ninth show, Curtain call, Aug 29, 1959 (Box 1, Reel 16)
  - Happy medium, Aug 22, 1959 (Box 1, Reel 17)
  - Jazz Fuegue, rehearsal of Ninth show, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 18)
  - Princess and the Pea, undated (Box 1, Reel 19)
  - Second show, Let the bells ring, Jul 09, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 20)
  - Third show, Silver screen, Jul 16, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 21)
  - Fourth show, Round robin, Jul 24, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 22)
  - Fifth show, Pocketful, Jul 30, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 23)
  - Sixth show, There you are, Aug 03, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 24)
  - Seventh show, There you are, Aug 03, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 25)
  - Eighth show, Silver, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 26)
  - Ninth show, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 27)
  - Eleventh show and final one, 1960 (Box 1, Reel 28)